[Music]
there's been a longstanding problem
among zookeepers of the gorilla a Latin
name gorilla gorilla gorilla the problem
is that they were throwing up all the
time we've never seen wild gorillas
barfing but it had unfortunately been
accepted as routine by many
zoos what were they feeding them well
you know they're big strong animals so
they made sure to feed them lots of
protein you know cottage cheese meat
eggs milk until a zoo and Germany got
this radical idea to try giving them
their natural diet and the change
following the alterations to the diet
was astonishing I mean before the the
poor silver back was regurgitating and
vomiting during most of the day but by
the third day eating what they were
supposed to eat he and the rest were all
miraculously cured even just removing
milk from captive gorilla diets led to
significant improvements cow's milk was
historically considered an essential
item in the captive gorilla diet but
they showed that removal of milk from
the captive gorilla diet May reduce such
undesirable behaviors and may be a step
towards better approximating their
natural diet I mean giving an animal
milk after weaning giving an adult
animal milk milk is for babies and then
giving milk from a B Vine to a
primate what were these crazy zookeepers
thinking doesn't make any
sense reminds me of this Landmark study
81 children presenting with reflux
gastroesophageal reflux disease so they
were given drugs and 2third got better
but 27 kids still did not so they tried
eliminating cow's milk from their diets
and within 1 month mon all 27 were
cured symptoms of acid regurgitation
heartburn or both occur at least once a
week in 10 to 20% of adults in the
western world and about up to 25% of all
infants now it's normal for babies to
spit up occasionally that's not what
we're talking about it can actually get
quite serious up to a quarter of infants
present with regurgitation severe enough
for parents to seek medical help and it
may just be that they're sensitive to
cow's milk the symptoms of cow's milk
protein allergy overlap and may coexist
or complicate gird reflux even if
there's no formal dairy allergy per se
there appears to be some kind of cow's
milk hyper sensitivity among many
infants and children with severe reflux
there's all sorts of invasive tests you
can do like stick pH probes down the
poor baby's throat but probably the most
practical test in routine pediatric
practice is just a trial of a cow's milk
protein Elimination Diet for 2 to four
weeks in infants with reflux the gold
standard is what's called an elimination
and rechallenge protocol where you see
you know full resolution of symptoms via
strict elimination followed by
recurrence of the symptoms on
reintroduction of cow smoke protein and
when you do that it take 200 or so
infants diagnosed with reflux and then
not only put them on a cow's milk-free
diet but then do the challenge test 80 5
of the 204 infants with reflux were
actually suffering from a cow's milk
allergy or at least hypers sensitivity
or
something what we think is happening is
that our immune system attacks the
bovine proteins as understandably
foreign triggering an inflammatory
response which like irritates the nerves
lining your digestive tract and that
results in abnormalities in the rhythmic
contractions of the stomach triggering
the
regurgitation we're not just talking
talking about formula fed infants cow's
milk protein allogy can occur in
exclusively breastfed infants as intact
cow's milk proteins can be secreted in
breast milk if the mom drinks milk or
eats eggs it can get into her baby cowm
protein and other foreign proteins can
pass into human breast milk so breastfed
infants with regurgitation and vomiting
May therefore benefit from a trial of
withdrawal of cow's milk and eggs from
the mat etal diet and indeed that is now
the consensus recommendation of both the
North American and European Society for
pediatric gastron neurology hepatology
and nutrition anytime you see reflux
let's first try a therapeutic trial of
either cows milk protein free formula or
for infants who are breastfed a maternal
strict cows milk protein Elimination
Diet and so then we can potentially
treat the cause without using
unnecessary medications and certainly
before you start considering performing
any anti-reflux surgery on the poor
[Music]
kid